Guide to the Professor John Lienhard Papers
University of Houston Libraries
Professor John Lienhard Papers
1961-2006
2001-009
Lienhard, John
21.00 Linear Feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
The John H. Lienhard series of speeches and materials cover a diverse range of topics. The earliest speech dates from 1962 and the most recent in the collection dates from November 1997.
Biographical Information:
John H. Lienhard is the author and voice of the popular radio program, The Engines of Our Ingenuity. The show airs daily in the United States on Public Radio and internationally on Armed Forces Radio. For his work on Engines, he received the 1989 ASME Ralph Coates Medal for contributions to the public understanding of technology. He also received the 1991 Portrait Division Award from the American Women in Radio and Television, and the 1998 American Society of Mechanical Engineers Engineer-Historian Award. He was also named as one of the five finalists from among 1,300 entrants in the 1993 New York Festival International Radio Competition.
Lienhard is Professor Emeritus at the University of Houston. From 1989 to 2000, he served as M.D. Anderson Professor of Technology and Culture in the departments of Mechanical Engineering and History at the University of Houston, and from 1980 to 1989 he was Professor of Mechanical Engineering at the school. His research areas include heat transfer with phase change, hydrodynamic boiling theory, condensation, flashing, thermodynamics of phase change, dynamics of jets and sheets, and the history of technology. He is also an Honorary Member of the American Society of Mechanical Engineers (ASME) and a fellow of the American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS).
He was born in St. Paul Minnesota on August 17, 1930, and received his B.S. in Mechanical Engineering in 1951 from Oregon State College, an M.S. in Mechanical Engineering from the University of Washington in Seattle in 1953, and a PhD. in Mechanical Engineering from the University of California at Berkeley in 1961.
Lienhard has written hundreds of professional journal articles, along with several technical books. He maintains full scripts of Engines programs on the web at http://www.uh.edu/engines. The site presently serves some 30,000 visitors each week. Each year KUHF also produces an hour-long Engines-related compact disk of twenty or so Engines programs. Professor Lienhard is also a prolific speaker and has given approximately 1100 major addresses.
All information from this biographical sketch was taken from the Engines of Our Ingenuity web site or from information provided by Professor Lienhard.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
University of Houston; University of Houston -- Faculty
Personal Name:
Lienhard, John H., 1930-
Accruals:
2 slide rules, December 3, 2014
1 box archival materials, February 9, 2015
7 boxes CDs and cassettes, 4 binders of transcripts, May 22, 2015
1 box archival materials, June 22, 2015
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Scope and Contents
The John H. Lienhard series of speeches and materials cover a diverse range of topics. The earliest speech dates from 1962 and the most recent in the collection dates from November 1997. The vast majority of speeches from the collection were given between 1980 and 1997.
Detailed List of Contents
- Engines of Our Ingenuity Talks
  Scope and Contents
  This series is the largest in the collection consisting of over 600 talks given to various groups by Professor Lienhard between 1961 and 2002. The series is arranged chronologically and the talks retain the titles used by Dr. Lienhard.
  - Boiling Water - A Misunderstood Phenomenon, 10/19/61 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Mechanism of Bubble Formation, 1/17/62 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - New Direction In Engineering Education, A, 4/28/62 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Introduction to the Problem: The Relationship between knowledge..., 3/17/63 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Recent Work on Spray Forming Devices, 5/24/66 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Dynamics and Stability of Systems, The, 12/2/66 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Locked-In Vortex Shredding From Vibrating Cylinders, 5/4/67 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Surface Tension Phenomena, 5/26/67 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Talk for the University of Kentucky, Section AIAA, 11/4/68 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Talk For Argonne National Lab, 12/15/69 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Steam Engines and Frankenstein Revisited, 2/9/70 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Steam Engines, Frankenstein, and the Men Who Made Them, 3/12/71 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - How Far East of Eden?, 3/26/71 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Some Recent Work On Free Liquid Jet Dynamics, 11/12/71 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Eigenresponsibilities of Scholars and Intellectuals, 4/13/72 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Hydrodynamic Theory of Boiling, The, 2/16/73 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Some Reflections on Excellence, 4/25/73 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Undergraduate Education at UK, 8/22/73 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - The Language End-Game, 10/4/73 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Some Problems Involving Jet Stability, 6/6/74 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Boiling Heat Transfer Phenomena and Peak Heat Fluxes, 1/13/75 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Aspects of Flashing of Superheated Liquids, 4/16/75 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - On the Collapse of the Superheated Liquid (or Subcooled Vapor) States, 4/22/75 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Reflections of Heroic Materialism, 3/2/76 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - On the Collapse of the Superheated Liquid (or Subcooled Vapor) States, 4/22/76 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - History of the Steam Engine, 12/76 - 1/77 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Technological Growth Before and After the Middle Nineteenth Century, 4/14/77 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Rapid Depressurization of Water from BWR and PWR Conditions, The, 2/20/78 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Hydrodynamic Mechanisms of the Peak Boiling Heat Flux, The, 6/16/78 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Rapid Depressurization of Water from BWR and PWR Conditions, The, 6/78 - 7/78 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Prediction of Boiling Burnout, The, 10/25/78 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Acceleration of Technological Banquet, The, 4/16/79 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Prediction of Boiling Burnout, The, 5/8/79 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - About Technological Change, 9/18/80 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - About Technological Change, 10/17/80 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Hydrodynamic Predictions of the Critical Heat Flux in Boiling, 10/27/80 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Prediction of Boiling Burnout, The, 10/27/80 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - About Technological Change, 1/7/81 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Some Reflections on Excellence, 4/27/81 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - On Logic, Language and Mathematics, 9/81 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Homogenous Nucleation and Superheated Liquid State, 10/20/81 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Problems Associated with High Intensity Boiling, 2/23/82 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Hope, Despair, and Technology, 4/2/82 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Flow Boiling Heat Transfer, 6/14/82 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Hydrodynamic Theory of Boiling Burnout, The, 6/18/82 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Technology Change, 10/20/82 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Some Laminar Jet Problems in the Behavior of Free Jets, 6/17/83 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Personal View of Engineering Education --1984, A, 4/3/84 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Some Ideas about the Evolution of Western Technology, 5/23/84 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Who Am I?, 9/6/84 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - On the Origins of Western Technology, 10/19/84 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Spinodal Lines and Equations of State, 10/23/84 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Spinodal Lines and Equations of State, 4/18/85 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Some Ideas About Growth and Quality in Technology, 4/19/85 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Spinodal Lines and Equations of State, 10/23/85 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Current Studies of High-Flux, Slow-Boiling Heath Transfer, 11/11/85 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - John Kyndall and the Romantic Revolution, 1/86 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Properties and Behavior of Superheated Liquids, The, 5/13/86 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Feedback Mechanisms - Alexandria and Edinburgh, 11/14/86 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Spinodal Lines and Equations of State, 12/10/86 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - The Pain of Learning, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Spinodal Lines and Equations of State, 1/4/87 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Flow Boiling Burnout on Cylinders, 1/8/87 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Feedback from Alexandria to Edinburgh, 1/29/87 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - On the Origins of Western Technology, 3/18/87 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Influences of Subcooling on Burnout of Horizontal Cylindrical Heaters, 3/25/87 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - On the Origins of Western Technology, 4/2/87 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Cool It With A Baboon's Blood, 4/3/87 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - On the Origins of Western Technology, 4/23/87 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Technology, Culture, and Communication, 4/26/87 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - On the Rates of Technological Improvement, 5/4/87 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Rates of Technological Improvement, 5/6/87 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Feedback Principal - Alexandria and Edinburgh, 10/5/87 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Research, Money, and Universities, 10/6/87 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Feedback Mechanisms - Alexandria to Edinburgh, 11/10/87 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - On Women and Flight, 1/22/88 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Rates of Technological Improvement, 2/26/88 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Rates of Technological Improvement, 3/24/88 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Technology & the Renaissance, 4/4/88 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Spinodal Lines and Equations of State, 4/14/88 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Technology, Culture, and Communication, 4/20/88 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Zero-G, Micro-G, Large-G, and How to Save Money, 5/11/88 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - What People Said About Books in 1498, 5/24/88 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Rates of Technological Change, 6/24/88 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Technology and the Church - Part 1: Technology and Genesis, 9/25/88 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Technology and the Church - Part 2:, 10/2/88 (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - The Rise of Medieval Power Technology, 10/88 (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - Spinodal Lines and Equations of State, 11/10/88 (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - Rise of Medieval Technology and Engineering, The, 11/17/88 (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - On the Origins of Western Technology, 11/17/88 (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - The History of Controls: From Alexandria to Edinburg, 11/88 (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - The Road Out of Eden: Talk #3, 1/89 - 5/89 (Box 1, Folder 92)
  - The Road Out of Eden: Talk #4, 1/89 - 5/89 (Box 1, Folder 93)
  - About Words and Machines and Changing the World, 1/18/89 (Box 1, Folder 94)
  - Thinking Like an Inventor, 1/19/89 (Box 1, Folder 95)
  - Spinodal Lines and Equations of State, 1/26/89 (Box 1, Folder 96)
  - Rates of Technological Improvements, 1/26/89 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Invention - Making the Engines of our Ingenuity, 2/27/89 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Rates of Technological Improvement, 3/7/89 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - On Building The Engines of Ingenuity, 3/30/89 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - On Making the Engines of Our Ingenuity, 4/4/89 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - On Making the Engines of Our Ingenuity, 4/15/89 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Women in Mathematics, 4/22/89 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - On Making the Engines of Our Ingenuity, 5/27/89 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Road Out of Eden, The - Talk #5: Eden Remembered, 6/89 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Road Out of Eden, The - Talk #6: Thermodynamics and Theology, 6/89 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Road Out of Eden, The - Talk #7: Women, Mathematics..., 6/89 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Other Kindreds, Other Tongues And The Victorian Intellectual Machine, 6/19/89 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Who Made the Engines of Our Ingenuity?, 6/21/89 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Women, Mathematics, and the Creative Process, 7/27/89 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Road Out of Eden, The, 7/30/89 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Spinodal Lines and Equations of State, 8/10/89 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Adventure in Taking History Outside of the Academy, 9/20/89 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Women and Mathematics and Technology, 9/29/89 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Feedback and Revolution, 9/29/89 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Road Out of Eden, The - Part 1: Leaving Eden, 10/1/89 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Road Out of Eden, The - Part 2: Medieval Religion..., 10/8/89 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Road Out of Eden, The - Part 3: Christianity and 18th Century Revolution, 10/15/89 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Spinodal Lines and Equations of State, 10/19/89 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Road Out of Eden, The - Part 4: Church & Victorian Intellectual Revolution, 10/22/89 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Road Out of Eden, The - Part 5: Eden Remembered: Adam and the Atom, 10/29/89 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - On Making the Engines of Our Ingenuity, 11/1/89 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Rates of Technological Improvement, 11/2/89 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Road Out of Eden, The - Part 6: Thermodynamics and Theology, 11/5/89 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Road Out of Eden, The - Part 7: Women, Mathematics..., 11/12/89 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Rates of Technological Improvement, 11/15/89 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Engines of the West, 12/1/81 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Who Made the Engines of Our Ingenuity, 12/12/89 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Road Out of Eden, The - Part 1: Leaving Eden, 1/90 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Road Out of Eden, The - Part 2: Medieval Religion, 1/90 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Road Out of Eden, The - Part 3: Christianity and 18th Century Revolution, 1/90 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Road Out of Eden, The - Part 4: The Church..., 1/90 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Road Out of Eden, The - Part 5: Eden Remembered; Adam and the Atom, 1/90 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Road Out of Eden, The - Part 6: Thermodynamics and Theology, 1/90 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Road Out of Eden, The - Part 7: Women, Mathematics..., 1/90 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Road Out of Eden, The - Part 8: The Anthropic Cosmological Principal, 1/90 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Rate of Technological Improvement and it's Relation to Innovation, The, 1/7/90 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Looking Inside the Inventive Mind, 1/16/90 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Looking Inside the Inventive Mind, 1/18/90 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Origins of Western Technology, 1/25/90 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Who Made the Engines of Our Ingenuity?, 1/28/90 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Women and the Life of the Mind, 2/7/90 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Rates of Technological Improvement, 2/15/90 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Making Nature and Dreaming Nature, 2/20/90 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Making Nature and Dreaming Nature - Part 2, 2/22/90 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Making the Engines of Our Ingenuity, 2/22/90 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Idiosyncratic View of 18th Century Revolution, An, 3/8/90 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Looking Inside the Inventive Mind, 3/14/90 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Freedom, Invention, and the Inventive Mind, 3/26/90 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Making the Engines of Our Ingenuity, 3/29/90 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Women, Math, and the Creative Process, 4/3/90 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Women and the Life of the Mind, 4/9/90 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Making the Engines of Our Ingenuity, 4/10/90 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Looking Inside the Inventive Mind, 4/19/90 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Search for the Boiling Curve, The, 4/20/90 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Looking for the Inventive Mind, 5/1/90 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Works of Our Hands, The, 5/1/90 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Free to Dream, Free to Build: 1776 - 1800, 5/9/90 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Looking Inside the Inventive Mind, 5/11/90 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Freedom, Invention, and Revolution, 5/23/90 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Flying Monk, Inventing the Wheel, Benzene Ring, The, 6/5/90 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Only Flame and Air, 6/11/90 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Origins of Machine Calculation, 6/16/90 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Rate of Improvement of Telescope, 6/16/90 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Some Thoughts About Egypt and Our Origins, 6/16/90 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Where Do Ideas Come From?, 7/13/90 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - America Comes Out of the Forest, 7/19/90 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - In Search of the Boiling Curve, 7/20/90 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - SGA Analog: An ASME Landmark, The, 8/17/90 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Reflections on John Fitch and Hamurabi, 9/10/90 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Where Do Ideas Come From?, 9/19/90 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Women and Science: A Search for Place, 9/20/90 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Frankenstein & Kubla Khan: Revolution in the Modern Age, 9/26/90 (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - Creative Role for Later Life, A, 10/2/90 (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Revolution and Technology, 10/2/90 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Reflections on John Fitch and Hamurabi, 10/5/90 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Where Do Ideas Come From?, 10/9/90 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Where Do Ideas Come From?, 10/11/90 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Women in Science, Engineering, and the Life of the Mind, 10/18/90 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - How We Got to the Golden Gate, 10/27/90 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Origins of Inventive Ideas, The, 11/2/90 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Women in Science and Technology, 11/13/90 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Women and Science: Does the Mind Have Gender?, 11/16/90 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Hand and Mind: Women in Engineering, 11/27/90 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Extensions of Our Ingenuity, The, 12/4/90 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Thoughts on Technical Education, 12/6/90 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Where Do Ideas Come From?, 12/10/90 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Where Do Ideas Come From?, 1/8/91 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Where Do Ideas Come From?, 1/9/91 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Engineer Looks at 18th Century Revolution, An, 1/10/91 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Where Do Ideas Come From?, 1/12/91 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - What Are Little Girls Made of?, 1/19/91 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Egypt On Our Minds, 1/19/91 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Women and the Life of the Mind: Concerns about the Workplace, 1/22/91 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Reading Japan in America's Past: The Search for America's Future, 2/6/91 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Impact of Science on Technological Improvement, 2/16/91 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Looking Inside the Inventive Mind, 2/18/91 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Invention vs. The Public Trust: The Essential Tension, 2/20/91 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Engines Over The Alleghenys: Technology Crosses the Mountains, 2/23/91 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Heat Transfer: It's History - The Japanese Change and Intellectual Vitality, 2/27/91 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Electric Words, Electric Thoughts: The Electric Sparks of Change, 3/5/91 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Some Thoughts About Patent Law, 3/14/91 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - In Search Of The Boiling Curve, 3/20/91 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Thoughts for an Honors Banquet, 4/18/91 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Reading Japan in America's Past: The Search For America's Future, 4/19/91 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Women in Male Preserves: Getting There, 4/20/91 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Reflections on the Creative Process, 4/23/91 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Machines Over the Mountains: Technology Goes West, 4/25/91 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Looking Inside the Inventive Mind, 4/26/91 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Road Out of Eden, The - Part 2:, 5/91 - 10/91 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Road Out of Eden, The - Part 3: Iron John, 5/91 - 10/91 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Road Out of Eden, The - Part 4: Eve Learns Science and Medicine, 5/91 - 10/91 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Road Out of Eden, The - Part 5: Eden Remembered; Adam and the Atom, 5/91 - 10/91 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Road Out of Eden, The - Part 6: The Anthropic Cosmological Principle, 5/91 - 10/91 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Earth, Air, Fire, Water, and More, 5/7/91 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Victoria "Dutch" Windmill, ASME Landmark, The, 5/7/91 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Women, The Mind, and Education?, 5/9/91 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Where Do Ideas Come From?, 5/17/91 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - In Search of the Boiling Curve, 5/17/91 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Roles of Innovation in Industries, The, 5/21/91 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Eye of the Forehead, Eye of the Mind, 5/21/91 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Women In the Life of the Mind; The Struggle for Place, 5/23/91 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Killing the Golden Goose, 5/30/91 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Looking Inside the Inventive Mind, 6/5/91 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Green's Bayou No. 1, First Outdoor Steam Turbine Generator, 6/9/9 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Women in the Life of the Mind: The Search for Place?, 6/11/91 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Iron John, 6/12/91 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Killing the Golden Goose, 6/26/91 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Making Japan: Making America: Making Things, 7/9/91 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Looking Inside the Inventive Mind, 8/2/91 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Many Faces of an Academic Scholar, The, 8/22/91 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - High-Rise Air-Conditioned Office Building: 1928 The Milam Building, 8/23/91 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Invention vs. The Public Trust: The Essential Tension, 9/13/91 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Earth's Age - Or Agelessness: Burnet, Hutton, Rayleigh, and More, 9/19/91 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - On the Preservation of Knowledge, 10/2/91 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Art, Technology, and Other Vulgarities, 10/4/91 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Women and the Healing Arts, 10/7/91 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Anthropic Cosmological Principle, The, 10/16/91 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Killing the Golden Goose: Reflections on American Inventiveness, 10/19/91 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Through a Child's Eyes, 10/22/91 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Engines of Our Ingenuity, 10/26/91 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Road Out of Eden, The - Part 8: The Anthropic Cosmological, 10/27/91 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Making the Familiar Strange, 11/8/91 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Alchemy to Modern Science, 11/14/91 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Success Through Failure: Reflections on the Creative Process, 11/20/91 (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - End of Alchemy, The, 11/24/91 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Rates of Technological Improvement, 11/25/91 (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Earth's Age - Or Agelessness: Burnet, Hutton, Kelvin, and More, 1/8/92 (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Art, Technology, and Other Vulgarities, 1/17/92 (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Fall of Alchemy and The Rise of Modern Science --1527 to 1637, The, 1/17/92 (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - New View of Christian Materialism Thermodynamics and the Church, A, 2/11/92 (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Making the Familiar Strange, 2/20/92 (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Women in the Sky, 2/25/92 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Scientific Literacy, 2/27/92 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Reflections on Failing and Succeeding, 2/27/92 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Making the Familiar Strange, 2/29/92 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Women and the Healing Arts: 2500 Years in a Struggle for Place, 3/4/92 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Women and the Healing Arts: 2500 Years in a Struggle for Place, 3/4/92 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - That Thou Art Mindful - Part 1: In God's Image, 3/11/92 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Search for a Definition of General Education in the Year 2000, A, 3/12/92 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - That Thou Art Mindful - Part 2: Adam's High Middle Age, 3/18/92 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Living Network, A, 3/25/92 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - That Thou Art Mindful - Part 3: The Apple and Eve, 3/25/92 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Scientific Literacy, 3/26/92 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - That Thou Art Mindful - Part 4: Eye of the Forehead: Eye of the Mind, 4/1/92 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Reflections on Failing and Succeeding, 4/6/92 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - That Thou Art Mindful - Part 5: The Anthropic Cosmological Principle, 4/8/9 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Feedback and Revolution, 4/28/92 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Killing the Golden Goose, 5/2/92 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Reading Japan in America's Past: The Search for America's Future, 5/19/92 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Electric Words, Electric Thoughts: The Electric Sparks of Change, 6/15/92 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Engines of Communication, 6/17/92 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Engines of Communication, 6/24/92 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Equations of State and Spinodal Lines: A Review, 7/5/92 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Looking Inside the Inventive Mind, 7/10/92 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Brief History of Power Production, A, 7/16/92 (Box 4, Folder 24)